Trading was hard until I understood
this. I wasn't struggling in trading
because the market is hard to read. I
was struggling in trading because I
didn't understand how to read the
language it was speaking [music] to me
every single day. Every single wick,
every single candle, every single high,
every single low. Whenever the market
does a move, sometimes it wants to tell
you that it wants to get stronger.
Sometimes it's going to tell you that
it's going to get weaker. It's going to
get lower or sometimes that it's going
to do absolutely nothing at all. And the
problem with most beginner traders is
that they don't know how to read this
language. They see red candlesticks,
they want to sell. They see blue
candlesticks and they want to buy. But
for experienced traders that they're
looking at these exact same candlesticks
that beginners traders are confused on
what a red or blue candlestick means,
their understanding of the market is at
a high point, low point, or even if it's
a market that's ready to enter. Now,
this language that is spoken inside of
the markets is what is called price
action. Now, I've been executing trading
with price action for the last 6 years
and it lets me know if a trade setup is
strong, if a trade setup is weak, or if
a trade setup is not even ready to have
a move. And in this video, I'm going to
break down to you exactly what price
action is and how you can take advantage
of it every single day. So, let's get
right into it. So, first things first,
let me give you a little bit of context
on exactly what price action is. Price
action is the way the market
communicates just on a nonverbal way.
It's almost like if you were to ask me a
mathematical equation that I have no
idea how to solve it and I go
I'm shrugging my shoulders. I'm not
verbally communicating it to you, but my
body language is meaning that I don't
know. But you understand how to read
that body language. Now, the problem
with 99% of traders that they don't
understand is that the market
communicates very much like body
language, but people just aren't
educated on how to read that type of
language because it's in a nonverbal
format. Every single high, every single
low, every single open, every single
close, every single wick, every single
candlestick is communicating something
to you. You just have to understand on
how to read that. So, price action is
how the market communicates on a
non-verbal way, no different as if I
were to shrug my shoulders on a question
that I don't know how to answer. Now,
with that being said, let's dive right
into the charts and let's break down the
difference between the first important
part to understanding price action. What
is a strong candlestick versus what is a
weak candlestick? Now, not every single
candlestick is identified the same. Now,
certain strong candlesticks can form on
higher time frames and then weaker
candlesticks form on higher time frames.
It also depends on the actual session
that these candlesticks are being
presented. And you need to understand if
a strong candlestick is happening in or
out of session. So, a couple of these
things go in sync. I'll be educating you
on all of that right this second. So,
let's break down the difference between
a strong and a weak candlestick.
Obviously, at first glance, you would
assume that whatever candlestick that is
the biggest would be what is called a
strong candlestick. Now, yes, that
[music] is quite obvious, but not
necessarily. Not every big candlestick
means that it is a strong candlestick
[music] and not every little candlestick
means that it's a weak candlestick. It's
actually more of market placements and
where that movement is actually
happening from. So, if you notice this
big candlestick, giant enormous bullish
candlestick, you would anticipate that
right after that move, what would you
have? You would have a continuation push
to the upside, right? You expect such a
big move that you would expect for it to
to continue to go to the upside. Well,
wrong. What ended up happening after
such a big move is it actually had a
complete reversal candlestick that came
all the way back. So, this big
candlestick isn't much of a strong
candlestick, as you can tell, because it
didn't continue to have that momentum to
the upside. But,
if you were to look at this candlestick
right before it, it's a very small
rejection candlestick. This candlestick
caused for the following candlestick to
have this push to the upside. So, you
can't confuse a small candlestick for
weak. Now, just because it's small, it
doesn't mean that it's weak. Just
because it's a larger candlestick, it
doesn't mean that it's strong. It's
where this candlestick is being placed
and how can that impact [music] the
trade? For example, if you were to have
a candlestick to be formed equally just
like this one, but this would be formed,
for example, right here in the middle of
this move, this would be considered what
is called weak because it's happening in
the middle of the chart. It's not really
doing anything. [music]
But, this candlestick, the reason why it
could be considered strong is because it
is approaching a strong level of support
where the last time that we were at this
area, we had a massive reaction to the
upside. It's our first time approaching
here, and we have clearly rejected it.
And that is what caused this then big
candlestick to have this push to the
upside. So, a strong candlestick, what
makes it strong is where that
candlestick is actually happening. It's
almost like if you were to be
a big strong bodybuilder amongst a a
bunch of other big strong bodybuilders.
You're not really that strong at that
area. But, if you're a big strong
bodybuilder and you're in a room full of
normal people, you stand out. So, it's
where you are placed at you would
actually stand out and have
significance. So, this is essentially a
big strong bodybuilder in a in an area
where whenever it's here, it obviously
has a reaction to the upside. So, this
is the understanding of price action.
For example, as you can tell, we come
back into the same area once we were
here once again, and we have the exact
same pattern that repeats itself. The
exact same type of candlestick that
happened here,
that happened here, happened here once
again. So, this [music] is what we call
a doji candlestick rejection, and I'll
break all those down in just a second.
But, this is a strong candlestick
because of where the market is placed.
and clearly it caused the exact same
reaction. It caused this market to have
a total push to the upside, very much
how it's done one time over here. So, as
you can tell, these candlesticks have
caused this move right here. This one
candlestick caused this exact same move
right over here, and it caused the exact
same move as well as over here. So, the
beauty of understanding what is a strong
and a weak candlestick is not falling
for what is these momentum traders,
right? These people that just look for
an impulse move. Now, I enter the trades
before the impulse. They wait for the
impulse, and they wait for that
momentum, and they just hop in for a
very small move. These are these
scalpers, these ICT guys, these SMC
guys, which could work, but they're not
catching the real duration of the move
because they're just doing stuff
impulsively. So, this is what a strong
candlestick would look like because we
are at a key area, and [music] it is
followed by the push. So, this is a
strong candlestick. A weak candlestick
would be the exact same one, but in the
middle of the chart where there's no
real support or resistance, where
there's nothing that's really holding
that candlestick up. So, what makes a
candlestick strong, to summarize, is
that it is placed correctly at an area,
and what makes it weak is that it's just
in the randomness of the land of the
charts.
Now, not the actual size will define the
strength of the candlestick. Remember
that. Moving on to the next subject when
it comes to understanding price action,
which is the language that we are going
to learn how to speak right now, is
wicks. Wicks are every single one of
these tails that you see to the upside,
to the downside. You can call them
wicks, you can call them hairs, you can
call them lines, you can call them
whatever you want, right? People get
super creative and always give them a
different reason or a different purpose.
What a wick is, it's basically a trail.
The market was a once upon a time at
that area could not any longer be at the
area and it was pushed to the other
side. This price was at one point all
the way at that high. So, if I'm going
to put my playback here a little bit
slower, I'm going to put it at half the
speed. When the market opened up the
candlestick, the following candlestick,
I still going way too fast, but this
candlestick opened up and when it
opened, it went all the way up here. So,
the market opened, it did a move like
this, it looked like a full bullish
candle, and then what ended up happening
after is that sellers came into the
market, whatever, decided to push price
to the downside, and then it ended up
closing like this. So, it's the trail
that the market was once upon a time at
that area. Now, this could be looked at
two different types of ways. It could be
looked at as a rejection, or it could be
looked at as a wick fill. The two very
different things and they can look
literally identical. So, what a
rejection is is what these would be
considered. These wicks over here means
that this market was trying to break
through this area and it couldn't, so
then it went to the upside. This right
here is a rejection because clearly the
market at one point was a full bearish
candlestick like this, tried to break
through this area, but it couldn't. So,
it rejected and then it went to the
upside. Once again, this is the exact
same thing but multiple times. The more
times you get this, the better. One time
here was a red candlestick, it couldn't,
then here was an also once again a red
candlestick and it couldn't, and it
ended up closing to the upside. So, this
right here is what would be called a
rejection because it is rejecting a
support. This could also be considered a
rejection at this area here because this
could be a resistance, for example,
right? If I were to draw a little box
right here, this is technically a
resistance. So, you can get the
rejection wick way whether you're at a
support or resistance. The price at one
significant point once upon a time was a
full bullish candlestick here and then
guess what? We rejected. This next
candlestick was a bullish candle trying
to break through and then we closed
below and we rejected. And very clearly
we continue to have the push to the
downside. Same exact thing here. Once
upon a time we tried to break through
this area and we couldn't and we
rejected and then the price simply came
to the downside. By just understanding
this right here, you could have easily
made money on all three of these
positions just by having understanding
of support and resistance and price
action. Clearly it's rejecting. You just
go in the direction of where it's
rejecting. Now,
this is going to look very similar to
what is now called a wick fill. A wick
fill is quite the opposite but in the
favor of the direction. That is a bit
confusing. Don't worry, it's going to
make sense right now in just a second.
So for example, this candlestick right
here is what would be considered a
perfect wick fill. And it actually ended
up happening perfectly. So what a wick
fill is is when you have a candlestick
like this that is formed which is
technically a rejection of the direction
that we're supposed to be headed. But if
you know how to read price action, you
would know it's a wick fill. So as you
can tell this market would be
Technically you can call it bullish
because it has this support level and
we've clearly reacted from the support
level. The following so we have the
bullish candlestick that's rejecting
along with the the doji rejection.
Then you have what is called right here
as another rejection candlestick. So
this technically people could say, "Oh,
it's rejecting the EMA. It's rejecting.
It's going to head to the downside." And
I would actually look at this and I'd be
like, "That's actually a perfect wick
fill." Because what do I do? I go down
to then the 4-hour and when I go down to
the 4-hour, to me what I'm seeing here
is a beautiful retracement on this
market. And then I'm seeing a inverted
pattern, which we're going to get into
patterns right now, which would be a a
head and shoulders pattern that we're
kind of forming here. What I would see
is I would see this as a 4-hour
retracement,
and on the higher time frame it looks as
a rejection. But in reality, it's just a
retracement. So, this is
this essentially had to happen for the
market to create more impulse to
continue to go to the upside. So, at
once upon a time, yes, this candlestick
when it opened, it was a full bullish
candlestick. Sellers came in, drove
price back down, but it's been held up
by this massive support that we've
clearly reacted and rejected from three
times. So, what do you think is
stronger? This minor zone here that gave
price a little bit of a retracement to
the downside, or this massive support
that has held price up three times every
single times it's come to it?
Obviously, the support level that has
held price up. So, I'm not going to
not take this trade just And this is
what happens with majority of traders.
I'm not going to just take a trade
because of one candlestick and
completely remove an entire top-down
analysis and an understanding of the
market. Traders get distracted, they get
scared, they get confused because they
don't know how to react off of one
single candlestick, and their entire
analysis goes out the window because of
one candlestick that they don't know how
to read because they don't know how to
read price action. So, this one
candlestick right here won't completely
remove my interest from the trade
because I understand on the lower time
frame it's creating that retracement
that then that retracement is going to
give me the perfect entry opportunity to
then continue to take this trade to the
upside. So, following after that, I
would then anticipate for the next
candlestick for the 4-hour to create
that retracement and have the push up,
and then it would fill that wick. So, a
wick fill is in the direction
it's basically a rejection it looks like
a rejection in the direction that we're
looking to take. So, that's really just
the difference between a rejection and a
wick fill. People can get it very
confused and once you understand to read
it it's very powerful. Very obvious to
tell that this is a clear sell because
we're rejecting it. Very obvious to tell
that this is a buy because rejecting.
Now that you understand this should be
very obvious to anticipate a wick fill
understanding that it's going in the
favor of the actual trade that you're
interested in taking. Now, with that
being said I want to move on to our next
and most important section which is
going to be reversal patterns. So,
people overlook these patterns every
single day in the market because they
just don't understand how to read it and
they don't understand how to optimize
these patterns. Reversal patterns are
not a way of trading
and oh, I only trade off of a reversal
pattern or only enter a trade off of
this. No, a reversal pattern is added to
your top down analysis is added to your
support or resistance and it's added to
your entry point. It's almost like if it
were to be an extra seasoning on the
actual meal that you're already having.
It's not the entire meal but it gives it
a little bit more flavor and it makes it
more enjoyable. So, patterns make a
trade that much stronger. Makes it a bit
more clear. Gives it a bit more
confluence and direction but it doesn't
determine the entirety of the trade. I
take plenty of trades without having any
patterns and I won't take a trade if it
were to only just be a pattern trade.
It's very important that you guys
understand how to distinguish one from
another. So, there's many different
types of patterns. You have reversal
patterns and then you have continuation
patterns. I want to break down reversal
patterns right now. So, one of the main
reversal patterns that I trade is what
is called the head and shoulders
pattern. So, what ends up happening with
the head and shoulders pattern is the
head and shoulders will have
its formation at the high of a market.
Right now as you can tell, this market
is very much bullish, and you can almost
anticipate that this next leg here could
create another higher high push to the
upside. But, what could end up happening
from here is that this will create what
is called a reversal pattern, which is a
head and shoulders. A head and shoulders
pattern happens all the way at the high
of a market. This could be on the
1-hour, 2-hour, 4-hour, daily, weekly,
monthly, yearly, whatever time frame you
want to. But, obviously, the higher the
time frame, the stronger it is. And the
way of trading these reversal patterns,
and this is probably one of the most
beautiful parts about reading price
action, is never anticipating
the reversal [music] pattern. It's
trading the reversal pattern, and people
overlook this so many times. Because
people always want to anticipate at this
point right here. It's like, "Oh, this
is going to be that right shoulder that
the market's going to create. I want to
sell off of the right shoulder." [music]
Why do you want to sell off of an
anticipation? Trading already it has
enough anticipation as it is. You're
already anticipating it's going to go up
or down. Just have the most amount of
confluences or
added reasons to enter a trade that you
can possibly have. So, this trade right
here, don't take a trade off of
anticipating the right shoulder. Have
the confirmation that we've indeed
shifted the structure, and we've formed
the actual head and shoulders pattern.
And this is where you would enter the
position on when the pattern is formed.
The head and shoulders pattern is not
formed until we don't shift the
structure. This right here was a bullish
market. This right here is a higher
high, and then this right here is a
higher low. This market, as long as
we're above these highs and lows, will
be bullish. You guys should know this.
If you don't know this, hit that like
and subscribe button, and go watch my
other videos on market structure, highs
and lows, because it will break this
down to the T, right?
But, if you understand that this is a
bullish market, the reversal pattern
would only be valid once you shift this
structure. So, this is the higher low,
this is the higher high. Here, we would
have shifted the structure, making this
a bearish market. And then, what do we
also coincidentally have? We also have a
what is called a head and shoulders. So,
you can take the head and shoulders
reversal trade from
the break of that structure point. You
can wait for the retest of the neckline.
At that point, you can get as creative
as you want with what makes you feel the
most comfortable with the position, but
you only take the pattern once you have
the confirmation that the pattern
exists. Don't anticipate that the
pattern will exist. There's no different
in this from a inverse head and
shoulders. So, an inverse head and
shoulders is a market that's hit a low
point, and we have created the exact
same pattern, but on obviously the
opposite side. It's a market that's hit
a bottom, and it's reversed, and now
it's going to head to the upside.
Head and shoulders, it's a market that's
hit a high, it's going to reverse, and
now start heading to the downside. You
can show you this example right here.
This market was heading to the upside,
but I mean, look at it right here. This
does not get any more clear than this.
This market was having a push to the
downside, lower high and lower low. Hits
the low point, and once this market hits
the low point, we then create this head
and shoulders pattern. After we create
this head and shoulders pattern, we
start heading to the upside. After we
head to the upside for quite some time,
what do we do? Then we create over here
another head and shoulders pattern right
here, and then we head to the downside.
Hit the high point, left, head, right
shoulder, and in this area over here, we
hit the bottom of the market, left,
head, and right shoulder. It's almost
like
playing words with Waldo. As soon as you
see it, you almost can't unsee it. And
it happens every single time at that not
every single time. It has a very high
probability of happening seven out of 10
times seven out of 10 times that you'll
get this reversal pattern.
But the most important thing is entering
once you have that actual shift of
structure. Head and shoulders is by far
my favorite reversal pattern that the
market can present at any given point. I
like to stick to it on the higher time
frames. It's just a lot stronger, more
respected, and you get a bigger risk to
reward on those positions, which means
in turn that you'll make more money.
Now, reversal patterns are absolutely
amazing, and I trade them all the time.
Now, the other favorite type of pattern
that price action feeds to you every
single every single day in the market, I
think more common than the reversal
patterns, but not quite as powerful, is
the breakout patterns. Breakout, break
and retest, consolidation break out,
accumulation, whatever you want to call
it. There's a thousand names out there
for it. But, it's basically where the
market is actually going in the
direction that it is already intended to
go. The reversal pattern is essentially
predicting a top or a bottom, and the
breakout pattern is doing quite the
opposite. You're literally continuing to
trade in the direction that the market
is headed at that very moment. For
example, I have a very simple breakout
pattern right here in multiple areas,
and I actually entered this trade live.
This is a real live trade that I
actually entered. This market right
here, as you can tell, it's stuck in
this support area. And when it's stuck
in this support area, you can anticipate
that the market was going to break out
of this zone. So, there was two possible
trades that I could have taken from this
position right here. I could have taken
a position either once it broke or once
it retested. But, it's in favor of the
direction that it's headed to. So, as
you can tell, this market was struggling
very much so to break through the
support level. Couldn't break once,
couldn't break three times, four times,
and then on the fifth time that it did
break, what happened? I waited for price
to come back, retest it, and give me my
rejection candlesticks. Now,
I entered this position and I took a
loss. It's okay. Part of the process.
Taking a loss is normal in trading.
What do I do? I took the exact same
trade once again. The market went back
up into this area, broke out of this
area once again, and it came back and it
retested. I waited for my exact same
rejection candlesticks, and then guess
what? I entered the position, and then I
won this trade. So, if in this trade I
lost 1%, in this trade I made back 6%,
I'm net positive 5%. I'm not scared to
take a loss, and I'm not scared to
reenter a position when the opportunity
presents itself. I'm confident in my
trading plan and in my rules and what I
do. So, this trade I entered the first
break and retest, didn't work out in my
favor. I entered in the second break and
retest, and it continued to go in my
favor. So, I could have entered on the
break, which is at this bearish
candlestick right here, and I could have
had the exact same stop loss, or I could
wait for that extra confirmation, which
is on the retest, which is what I do,
which is what I typically like to do.
So, if a market, for whatever reason is
consolidating, right? So, if we're just
create a bit of a consolidation market
right here,
and we're anticipating for us to enter
this position on the break and retest,
or the breakout, basically trade
continuation pattern. You can either
enter the position on the breakout as
soon as it breaks, or you can wait for a
retracement. The retracement is
obviously a lot stronger, and you're
going to have a lot more confirmation
that it can reject this area once again
and head to the upside, and you get
saved that it's not a fake out and then
it continues to go back to the downside.
It's impossible to avoid these fake
outs, but having this actual
break [music] and then retest
confirmation, waiting for a rejection
candlestick, will give you a much higher
probability of winning a position. So, a
lot of people make a major mistake, and
when they start having the trade make
that retracement, they're scared that
it'll come back into here, give them the
reaction really fast, and then that
they'll miss out on the position
entirely, which could be true, but
shouldn't determine your execution on
every single [music] trade. And you need
to stick to something consistently every
single time, so your results can have
the exact same recognition as what your
rules would be. If you change your rules
every single time, so will your results.
So, you can either enter the trade right
at the breakout, my least favorite. You
can enter the trade on the retest with
no confirmation, my least favorite out
of all of them. Or you can enter on the
retest with the rejection confirmation,
which is my favorite and my go-to
typically on eight out of 10 trades that
I were to take with this pattern. So,
this is the continuation pattern, the
breakout pattern that it goes in favor
of the market that you're actually
headed in every single week. And the
beauty of this is that the market gives
you this opportunity the majority of the
times on the lower time frames. So,
there's opportunities on day trades,
scalp trades of these. You just have to
be a bit more careful because they're a
bit less respected. And this is what I
break down every single week with my
students inside of my community, where I
give them the top pairs that I'm trading
for that specific week. I let them know
why they should be interested in
entering a reversal pattern compared to
a breakout pattern. I let them know why
this market has a higher probability of
going in one direction compared to the
other. Because in a market full of
abundance with endless amounts of
opportunities, it's very easy to get
lost. And it's okay to make mistakes.
That's why I have classes with my
traders where I personally, live in
front of other students, I review their
positions to make sure that what they're
doing is correct. And if they're
actually entering the trade for the
reasons that they assumed that they're
entering it. If you want to know more on
how to be my student, make sure to DM me
the word Sunday Swings. Just click on
the link down below. DM me that word.
Talk to one of my team members to see if
you're a right fit for us and if we can
help you out. But students that join the
community, they get access to the live
trades that we're looking at every
single week with these exact same
understandings of price action. And why
the market should have a higher
probability of going in one direction
versus the other. Because
patterns, reversal patterns, that's all
great, but it all comes down to price
action and what these candlesticks are
telling you. And with the craziness that
the market has been having lately with
fundamentals, wars, presidents being
abducted, or at least I don't know what
year you're watching this video in, but
very recently, the fundamentals have
been going crazy, and price action has
shifted, but the core foundations of it
are exactly the same. So, if you want to
know more about it, DM me the word
Sunday Swings. If you like this video,
hit that like and subscribe button, and
I'll see you guys in the next video.